At first, people said,
最开始大家说啊
you'd feel an earthquake in three hours.
你等三个小时就会那个地动山摇
They insisted you should stay close to the bathroom.
一定要在厕所附近
I said, 'No big deal.'
我说无所谓啊
But after waiting for three hours, there wasn't much of a reaction.
后来我等了三个小时也没有什么太大的反应啊
I just had to go to the bathroom once.
就上了一次厕所
I've already been to the bathroom twice today.
我今天已经上了两次厕所了
And just now, I went again.
刚才又上了一次
All together,
加一块
that makes four times.
一共是四次啊
By the time night fell,
等到夜里的时候
my stomach suddenly started rumbling like thunder.
突然之间就肚子里跟打雷了一样
It was like a whole orchestra playing drums and cymbals in there.
就各种各样的这个敲锣打鼓啊就来了
Then I thought, maybe it’s good to eat more probiotics.
然后觉得其实多吃点益生菌还是好
Actually, I have two types of probiotics at home.
我家里边其实有两两种益生菌
I usually don’t eat much.
我都平时没怎么吃啊
Actually, boosting your metabolism can prevent you from gaining too much weight.
其实就是提高一下人的代谢就不会这么胖了
Of course,
当然来讲的话
if you really want to lose weight, you should exercise.
想啊真正减肥呢还是要通过这运动啊
Whether it’s strength training or cardio,
不管是力量训练还是有氧训练
this is a healthy way to maintain your fitness.
这才是一个健康的维持的方法
You can’t rely solely on medication,
不能说光靠吃药
that’s just a waste of money.
那都是智商税
I’ve paid my fair share of that waste.
这智商税我就没少交啊
In this episode, I want to talk about a strategy for life.
我这期还想跟大家讲一个做人的策略的东西
Because everyone has been pretty upset about the 4+4 thing recently. It's really been bothering people. If I were to go back to my twenties, Not just my twenties, I mean, my body,
因为最近大家被这个4+4这事 弄得这个挺挺不开心的啊 我觉得如果我要是回到20多岁 别说回到20多岁吧 我就是身体啊
If I suddenly found myself back in my twenties,
我现在突然回到20岁的状态啊
If my age suddenly became 20 again,
年龄突然变到20岁
I'm talking about people born in 2005.
我说2005年出生的人的话
My feelings now are quite different.
我现在的感受会很不一样很不一样
But everyone has their own way, you know.
但是呢你说每个人都有每个人啊
Each era has its own dark night of the soul.
每个年代都有自己的这个灵魂的暗夜
Each has its own challenges to overcome.
都有自己需要克服的课题
There's no easy solution.
没有什么太好的办法
But I want to share this point with everyone.
但是我这一点跟大家说一说
When playing chess,
这个下象棋的时候啊
there's a method,
有一种方法啊
a winning strategy called the Three-Pawn Checkmate.
就是有一种胜利的方法叫做三兵逼宫
This method is something my dad loves to use.
这个方法呢是我爸特别爱用的东西啊
You all know about chess,
大家知道国际象棋
and Shogi from Japan,
包括日本的将棋
where when you reach the last rank, you can promote the piece.
走到最后一格的时候是可以升格的啊
I think it’s called something like a silver general turning into a gold general or something like that.
啊那叫什么银匠变金匠还是叫什么来着
Anyway, I don’t really understand Japanese chess,
反正就是日本象棋我不懂啊
but in chess, you know you can use a pawn,
但是国际象棋是知道你是可以用兵
to promote it to a queen.
变成王后的啊
But rather than talking about these things, My dad is quite into playing cards. And he also enjoys playing chess and the like. His strategic thinking in games has deeply influenced me. He plays cards really well.
但是与其说这种东西来讲的话 就是我爸他这个人玩牌呢 这个玩下棋呢之类的 他这个博弈的思想呢深深地影响了我 他玩牌也玩的非常好
I’ve inherited that from him.
我就是继承了他这一点
But I don’t gamble, you know.
但是我们都啊我我不反正我不赌博啊
I don’t have a gambling habit.
我不赌博不是好赌的
Dad loves to cry, Mom focuses on her studies, and my younger brother is very understanding.
爹爱哭的妈上学的弟弟
He’s very mature for his age.
懂事的
He's not like that, you know.
他不是这样呃
But my dad doesn't play anymore either.
但我爸现在也他也不玩
He's old, right?
老了嘛对吧
He stays at home now.
老了也在家
My mom is pretty strict with him.
我妈管她管的比较严呃
But he plays chess really well.
但是他下棋下的非常好
Three pawns checkmating the king.
三兵逼宫啊
Basically, it means using your least noticeable pieces.
其实就是说白了就用你最不起眼的子儿啊
to gain a strategic advantage
去取得战略上的优势
because you have five pawns
因为你兵有五个啊
two chariots, two horses, and two cannons
车两个马两个炮两个啊
most people prefer to use their chariots, horses, and cannons or to exchange them with the opponent's
一般人都是爱用车马炮或者爱换对方的车马炮
first, eliminate the opponent's superior forces
先把对方的这个优势兵力干掉啊
but they usually don't use the pawns
但是呢他们通常不会用兵啊
we say that using pawns skillfully is an art
我们说其实用兵如神啊
if you look at many people
其实你看的很多人
when it comes to philosophical aspects of life
世间的一些哲学上的东西来讲的话
Actually, when it comes to the Chinese people,
其实我们呃中华民族的这个人而言
our general philosophical literacy is quite high. In this regard, because Western countries promote a happiness-oriented education, and they intentionally aim to create
就是我们中国人在这个普遍意义上的哲学素养 上面来讲是比较高的啊 呃因为国外推行的是快乐教育 再加上他们有意的要创造
a distinction in culture and knowledge
这个有产阶级和无产阶级之间的
between the propertied and the propertyless classes.
这个文化跟知识上的区别啊
Therefore, they have private education systems with prestigious universities,
所以他们会有啊私立教育系统会有这个大学校
and so on.
会有这个啊
This joyful education encompasses a lot of aspects.
这个这个这个快乐教育会有很多东西
It actually widens the gap between the rich and the poor.
他把这个贫富之间拉的其实差别很大
His elite education is quite different from his education for the masses.
他的精英教育跟他的平民教育是两回事啊
Cough, cough, and then someone pointed out that
咳咳然后有人就说了啊
There's a 4+4 system in the country.
国内有4+4
We need to say that
我们要说啊
In many cases,
就是你很多的时候来讲
You can't prevent certain people
你没有办法阻止某一些人
From seeking advantages for their own children.
为自己的子女谋私利啊
This thing is what you're talking about completely.
这个东西是你说完完全全
It's not true that he doesn't consider his children.
他不为自己的子女考虑是不存在的
But in general terms,
但在普遍意义上来讲
To a greater extent,
更多的意义上来讲的话
It's not about recruiting thousands of people.
他这并不是说招收了几千个人啊
I'm not trying to defend this.
我不是在为这事洗地啊
Let me add,
我要再说
We can't say that,
大家不能说
Because of these corrupt elements.
因为有着这些啊蛀虫
With these people taking backdoors
有了这些走后门的人
you lose your own confidence
就自己失去了信心
you lose faith in your own life you develop a pessimistic attitude towards the world Don't be like that Why is it called a three-soldiers siege? We don't have any major pieces like chariots, horses, or cannons
自己对自己的人生失去了信心 自己对这个世界产生了悲观的一个情绪 不要这样 为什么说是三兵逼宫呢 咱们这些人没有什么车马炮啊
Rong was born just like you
天生下来你看荣哥其实跟你一样
He doesn't even own a car
名下还没有一辆汽车啊
Not a single car
没有一辆汽车
No house of your own
没有自己的房子啊
Haha, you must feel pretty unlucky to end up like this
哈哈就是那你混成这样也够倒霉的哈
You must feel pretty embarrassed, right?
你也你也够够丢人的对吧
It’s not a big deal
这也没什么
Actually, Brother Rong is in the same boat as you
其实荣哥在这方面跟你一样
But when it comes to Brother Rong
但荣哥唯一可能来讲
He does have one advantage over you
可以说就是比你有优势的地方呢
He managed to avoid some pitfalls
就是有些坑我没踩啊
This brings up that book I mentioned about avoiding pitfalls.
这就又提到了我避坑那本书啊
But that book isn't crucial.
但是那本书不重要啊
I think the book talks about many pitfalls in your life.
我书好像说的是你人生你人生中很多的坑啊
Financial pitfalls can be avoided if you're careful.
经济上的坑你只要不踩啊
Let's talk about the subprime mortgage crisis.
咱们说次贷危机啊
Mortgage, car loan, and renovation loan.
房贷车贷装修贷
And wedding gift loan.
彩礼贷
If you avoid all these four loan crises,
四贷危机你要都没有啊
Then you'll avoid many financial pitfalls.
再有这些经济上的一些坑
You just need to avoid it.
你只要避过去了啊
For example, when you have 10,000.
比如说1万的时候啊
We don’t buy phones on a whim.
咱不乱买手机
We don’t buy computers on a whim.
不乱买电脑
When you have 100,000, don’t buy a car on a whim.
10万的时候不乱买车
When you have 300,000, don’t invest recklessly. Don’t buy a house. When you have 1 million, don’t lend money recklessly. When you have 3 million, don’t engage in reckless activities. Don't get swayed by the big talk when you hit 30 million. Just like Brother Daxiang. So sometimes, as long as you avoid these pitfalls,
30万的时候不乱投资 不买房啊 100万的时候不乱借钱 300万的时候不乱搞 3000万的时候不乱听大哥给你忽悠 就像大祥哥那样似的 所以有的时候你只要把这个坑避开了以后啊
life can still be straightforward.
这个人生还是可以很坦荡的
You can live comfortably,
活得很舒服
very at ease.
很自在啊
It's definitely like that.
一定是这样的
When it comes to strategy,
然后大家在战略上来讲的话
maintain strategic focus.
保持一个战略定力啊
A confidence
一个信心
Just like our arduous Anti-Japanese War
就像咱们的这个艰苦卓绝的这个抗日战争
And the Liberation War
跟这个这个解放战争一样
Strategically, as long as we win
战略上咱们只要赢了
As long as the people are in charge
咱们只要是啊人民当家做主啊
Utilize unity
动用团结啊
The power of the people
这个人民的力量啊
Can mobilize the masses
能发动群众
That's the key point
就这一点东西
You rely on the people in your strategy
你在战略上依靠人民这个东西
The banner of strategy is right
战略的旗帜是对的
In the future, what you're actually doing in your life
以后呢你其实在做这一生当中呢
Oh, be honest and straightforward
哎呀要坦坦荡荡的
It doesn't matter
没有关系啊
We're discussing just the personal
我们讨论的只是个人的
Whether one can be completely economically independent
在经济上是否能够完完全全独立啊
But speaking of being not entirely independent
但是来讲不完全独立
That's fine too
那也没有关系
There's not much to it.
也没有什么太大的什么
You need to understand the difference between you and the rich kids.
你要知道你跟富家子弟之间区别是什么
It's that they have luxury cars.
就是他出入有豪车啊
They have better hobbies.
他玩的好一点啊
They have better partners.
他有更好的妞啊
And they eat better. That's about it. Then you think about the cost of this life. Look at me, I'm 40 years old. Do I envy them? If you ask me, I really did envy them when I was young. Back when I was young, all these things people have, in the process of competition,
然后吃的更好一点 也就是这样 然后你觉得这一生代价的话 你看我40岁了 我羡慕他们吗 你要说年轻的时候我是真羡慕 因为年轻的时候 人所有的这些东西在争斗的过程中
in the pursuit of mating rights,
在去寻求这个交配权的过程当中啊
comparing yourself to others,
跟人去比呀也好
having this competitive mindset,
有这种竞争心理啊
makes a person different.
那人是不一样的
But by the time you hit 40,
等到40岁这个关口说
You suddenly feel that many people die in their thirties or forties.
你突然觉得就是很多人三四十就死了
And they didn't even live as long as I have.
然后寿命都没活过我
So don't compare these things with me.
你再跟我比这些
Don't compare health with me either.
你再跟我比健康
You can't outdo me.
你也比不过我
If you compare hair volume,
你比发量
At this point, if we compare again,
这时候再去比一比
Some people's family backgrounds are just not as good.
有些人的家境就差了
All of a sudden, this rich second generation
突然之间这富二代
many people aren't as impressive as they used to be
很多人就不像以前那么牛逼了
but of course, the truly impressive ones remain so
当然牛逼的人还真牛逼
while those who aren't impressive sometimes fall halfway
不牛逼的人有时候就下了一半
you'll suddenly realize
你会突然发现呃
how they rose to great heights
真的是见他起高楼
and then, how to put it
见他就是怎么说呢
they fall back to their original state
又跌回这个原状
so there are many people like this
所以很多这样的人啊
After reaching a high level of development,
高啊经过高度的这个发展以后呢
he then experienced rapid growth with high debt,
他又经过高速的就是有高负债
so often times,
所以很多的时候
we say a person's life has its ups and downs several times, don't get too anxious all of a sudden, saying I'm 20 and haven't, saved up a million by 30, I haven't reached 30, and haven't established my own business by 35. It hasn’t gone public yet. I feel like such a failure.
我们说这人这一辈子起起落落好几次 千万不要一时着急 说我20岁没有在30岁之前啊 攒够100万啊 我没有30 35岁之前没有建立一个自己的企业 没有上市 我觉得自己好失败
Don’t think like that.
不要这么想
Look at me, I’m still nothing.
你看我现在还狗屁
That’s not true, right?
不是呢对吧
I’m only getting there by June this year.
我到今年6月啊
I can only get a slot on either May 26th or 28th this year.
今年5月26号还是28号才能排上一个
I still have to use it.
还得用
My parents
我爸妈
in this three-generation family with my son
用我儿子的这个三代人家庭
have to enter a lottery to get a license plate
摇号才能摇到一个牌
but what use is a car to me?
但你说车对我来说有什么用呢
I don’t commute these days
我现在也不通勤
right?
对不对
So owning a car is more about face
所以车这个东西呢就是一个面子的事
and I still have to pay for depreciation
我还要为他付折旧费
and insurance
保险费
Parking fees
停车费啊
In Beijing
在北京啊
In congested areas
堵车的地方
Generally speaking
通常来讲呢
the drivers' skills are not great
车夫的这个技术都不好
In places where there's no traffic
真正不堵车的地方
like outside the Sixth Ring Road
你像六环外啊
drivers from outside the Fifth Ring Road and in county towns
五环外还有这个县城的司机
their driving skills are excellent
那车技都非常好啊
This is a young follower of mine.
这是我一个粉丝小妹妹
She's a girl from Xi'an, WBY.
她西安的一个小妹妹WBY
She said,
他说的说
the less developed the transportation is,
越是这个交通啊不发达
the places where there's no traffic jam,
不堵车的地方
the better the drivers' skills tend to be.
这个司机的这个车技越好啊
Places like where you are, with constant traffic jams, don't really help to hone those skills.
越是像你这种堵车的地方也练不出来啊
People tend to go out less often, spending their days stuck in traffic. How do you practice? Right? You're just practicing how to handle traffic accidents, right? This one is actually practiced quite well. To train your temperament, right? To practice road rage. This can actually be practiced.
一出行就少 天天堵在路上 你怎么练 对不对 你就嗯就是练这个如何处理交通事故了 这倒是练的挺好 练你的心性对不对 练路怒症 这个都能练出来
But other things can't be practiced.
但是别的东西练不出来
So when it comes to it,
所以来讲的话
Everyone has their strengths
咱们说尺有所长
and their weaknesses.
寸有所短啊
I'm in this situation in Beijing
我就在北京这种状态下
You say I can't match Wang Sicong
你说我干不过王思聪
Can't match him, can't match him
干不过干不过不
Why do I have to outdo him?
我为什么一定要干过他
Why do I have to outdo her?
我为什么一定要干过她
I can't be like these Ms. Dong
我不如这些什么董小姐
Then I won't be like her.
那就不如她吧
But I look better than her.
可我长得比她好看
I'm smarter than him.
我比他聪明啊
And he's now in disgrace.
而且他现在身败名裂了
My life is going better than his.
我人生状况比他好啊
He might just have a bigger house.
他可能就是房子住的大一点
Drive a better car.
车开的好一点
But I don't live in my car all the time.
但我也不是天天住车里啊
Live in a bigger house.
房子住大一点
You still have to sleep in one bed, right?
你不是也得睡一张床吗对吧
Your reputation is ruined, isn't it?
名声搞臭了对吧
Your life has been wasted this way.
人生就这样耽误了
You're currently staying in America to wait for production capacity.
你现在在美国待产能
There's no such thing as an anchor baby in America anymore, right?
现在美国也没有anchor baby了对吧
Do you think you'll have to come back?
你是不是还得回来呀
Isn't that right?
对不对
You'll still have to come back with your tail between your legs.
你还是得灰溜溜的回来
Or how do you manage to stay abroad?
或者你在国外就怎么样
What do you think life abroad is like?
你说在国外的生活是什么样
I've seen it too
我也见识过
right?
对不对
It's just about eating a bit better
无非就是吃的好一点
sleeping a bit better
睡得好一点
dressing a bit better
穿的好一点
There's not much to it really
其实没有什么太大的东西
Do you think clothes are that important?
你说穿的东西很重要吗
If you don't care about appearances
如果你不在意面子的时候
you might find that food, clothing, and cars aren't that important The one thing I'm really particular about is the house. I think it should be a bit bigger. So I can practice with swords and spears. And even shoot arrows inside. I think that would be great. But I also have cats at home.
你会觉得吃穿跟车可能都不重要 我唯一比较有执念的就是房子 我觉得房子大一点啊 可以舞刀弄剑 可以在家里边射箭 觉得挺好 可我家里还有猫呢
What if they get hurt?
万一伤到猫怎么办
What if a child gets hurt?
万一伤到孩子怎么办
So as I get older,
所以岁数大了以后
When it comes to martial arts skills,
对这些啊武艺上面来讲的话
the requirements aren't as high.
要求就不是那么高了
I've realized that in this lifetime,
所以我发现人这一辈子哈
I feel that living near the second ring road now,
我现在觉得住在这个二环边上
having a smaller house is actually quite nice,
房子小一点也挺好啊
it's not a big deal,
也没有什么啊
I don't have a car,
没有车
but since I don't commute, it's actually pretty good,
但是我又不通勤也挺好的
right?
对不对
Friends who dress up a bit more
穿的好一点的朋友
I have just one piece of clothing per season
我一个季就一件衣服
I only have one pair of shoes
我就一双鞋啊
unlike others who have 300 pairs in their shoe cabinets
不像别人鞋柜里300双鞋啊
a whole wardrobe can't even fit them
一个衣柜都塞不下
they need six wardrobes
塞六个衣柜
a pile of bags
一大堆包
and they even have a dedicated wardrobe
还专门有一个衣柜
I think it’s like this
我觉得这样来讲
Aren't you just falling into the trap of consumerism?
你不就掉进消费主义陷阱了吗
And when I ultimately die,
而我最终死的时候
I can't take those things with me.
那东西也带不走啊
Right?
对不对
I can't take them with me.
也带不走
They'll just be left in the grave for others.
那坟墓里边就给别人留的了
Right?
对不对
The thing I have the most at home now is books.
我这家里边现在最多东西就是书啊
Books aren't of much practical use.
书没有什么太大用啊
You can just toss it after reading.
就看完了就随时扔
You can just give it away after you're done.
看完了就随时就送人了
It's not that useful anyway.
也没有太大用啊
I don't plan to keep it as a treasure.
我也没有说珍藏
Unlike my books.
不像我的书
I would definitely keep many copies of my own series. But now, a lot of books get thrown out once they're read. They get tossed after reading. So you'll find that you don't need a lot of things in life.
我自己的那个B坑我肯定会珍藏好多本啊 但是呢现在就是很多书就是看完了就扔 看完了就扔 所以你会发现你人生中并不需要很多东西
So you need to make a lot of money
所以你要赚很多钱
The reason to acquire a lot of things doesn't exist
要获得很多东西的理由就不存在
I was born not caring much about food and clothes
我天生就不在意吃穿啊
I might care a bit more about food
我可能在意点儿吃
But if you can cook for yourself
但吃的话如果自己能做饭
If you buy the ingredients and cook yourself
自己买原材料做的话
Isn't it much cheaper
是不是就便宜的多
Right
对不对
But now there's food delivery
但是现在有外卖
I need to order enough food to make use of the discount.
外卖要凑凑足了
With the coupons, I can still enjoy some really delicious meals.
券里我也可以吃到很好吃的东西
Let's talk about the food.
吃上边来讲吧
Everyone has pretty much evened out.
大家已经拉平差不多了
I guess everyone buys those luxury items at a 10% discount through DHgate.
穿你想大家都通过敦煌网买那个一折的奢侈品
Is wearing fancy clothes that important?
穿很重要吗
And who am I dressing up for anyway?
而且我穿我穿给谁看呢
Am I dressing up for my relatives?
我穿给亲戚看吗
Or for my classmates?
还是穿给同学看
I don't really keep in touch with them
我跟他们都不怎么来往
How am I supposed to show them?
我怎么去给他们看呢
Right?
对不对
It doesn't make much sense anyway
也没有意义啊
It's not like the feeling at the village entrance
是不是又不是村口村口那种感觉
I bought a good car
我买了车买的好
The weather is bad
雨不好
Who am I going to show it to?
我给谁看呢
I'll just show it to my followers
也就给粉丝看
I might as well go out in the sun
我我自己要不晒呢
no one cares who cares
也没人在意谁在意
I really want to buy the Xiaomi 13 Ultra, but it's too expensive maybe I should get a Wuling Hongguang instead just to secure a license plate spot spend ten or twenty thousand on a used one maybe just leave it be like how Brother Rong left his battery to go bad my goal is to let it go bad It's just so that I can have a license plate when I need one.
我真买小米苏7ultra烧得慌 还是我买一个五菱宏光 占个车牌位啊 花个一两万买个二手的 是不是放着就放着吧 说荣哥那样电池都放坏了 我目的就是为了放坏了 就是为了有的时候我能够有车牌就完了
So my goal is to prevent trouble.
所以我的目的就是为了防坏
Right?
对不对
My goal is to be indifferent when the time comes.
我的目的就是为了到时候无所谓
I still have to pay for his insurance and parking fees.
我还得为他付保险费跟停车费呢
That just annoys me even more.
这我就更烦啊
Having a license plate would actually be more of a hassle.
有了车牌反而更烦
Because I don't have a place to use it.
因为我没地儿去用去
I'm doing fine with my electric vehicle now.
我现在用电动车挺好
I don't even need a motorcycle.
摩托车都用不着
I just have a few hundred meters to go every day right from my doorstep.
我天天在门口就这么几百米
A single charge lasts me a whole month.
我充一次电能使一个月
Why would I need to refuel?
我干嘛要加油呢
I’d have to drive all the way out of the Third Ring Road to refuel.
加油我还得跑三环外边
And risk getting points on my license from the police.
然后还得冒着这个被警察记分
It’s a 200 yuan fine and one point deduction for breaking the driving restrictions.
扣200块钱记一分的这个标准
Because I violate the driving restrictions.
因为我闯限行
Right?
对不对
I can't afford a 300,000 Beijing A license plate
我买不起30万的京A
So you'll find that the more you possess
所以很多东西你会发现你占有的越多啊
the more you own
你拥有的越多
the more burden you carry
你这个负担越多
If I buy several apartments, I'd have to rent them out
你说我买几套房子还得出租啊
and deal with the hassle of renovations
还得给装修多烦
Buying a car means dealing with depreciation
买车还得折旧
and worrying about rain damage
还得怕淋雨
and having to shield it from the sun
还得怕还得给这遮阳
I’m worried the summer heat might melt it.
夏天又怕他给晒化了
Right?
对不对
What a hassle.
又多烦啊
And dealing with multiple wives,
弄那好几个媳妇
which one is going to get pregnant? Then they’ll come after you for child support. How much of a headache that would be. Right? Your garage is such a mess. Clothes for wearing and such Won't need them in a couple of days They're no longer useful So you might as well donate them, right?
哪个媳妇儿怀怀怀孕了 回头还还得跟你要抚养费 要多烦 对不对 你这东西车房乱七八糟 吃穿穿的衣服之类的 过两天不用 没用了 也就捐了对吧
Or just throw them away
也就扔了
You won't be seeing them anyway
你也见不着
And they take up space
还得给它占地方
And you end up buying bigger storage because of the clothes and shoes
还因为占了衣服和鞋子的地方还得买大
Isn't that so?
是不是
It's just that why do you call it a big house?
其实就是你的东西为什么叫大房子
It's because you've bought so much stuff.
就是你买的东西太多了
But you've bought too many things.
可是你买的东西太多
Look, I have six lighting kits now.
你看我现在六个摄影灯啊
I always only have one camera.
摄像机我永远只有一台啊
But now I have a sports camera.
但是我现在有一个运动相机
Do you have two or are there four or five game consoles?
有两台是不是游戏机好四五个
I can handle what I'm playing now.
我现在玩的过来
How long has it been since I touched the Steam Deck?
mosteam deck多长时间没碰了
It would have been better to smoke.
还不如抽了呢
Right?
对不对
How long has it been since I last used my Switch?
我的死switch多长时间没用了
I only went on business trips eight times this year, right?
我这一年初才出八次差对吧
Only ten times.
才出十次差
I don’t really have anywhere to use such things.
我也没有地儿去用这种东西
There’s actually no use case for it.
其实没有使用场景
I spent a lot of money buying things.
我买了花了钱买了很多东西
There’s really no use case for them at all.
根本就没有使用场景
So you really got here
所以你真正到你啊
The day you actually become a monk
哪天真是出家了
Or go and be a Taoist
或者当道士去了啊
Or go and become a priest
或者去当神父去了
Or go and become a monk
或者去当一马木去了
That's fine
这没关系啊
We'll handle it based on different religions
这个咱们根据宗教不同
We'll make sure everyone gets a fair share
咱们就都啊雨露均沾
But it doesn't have any practical significance
但是没有实际意义
I mean, the wealth you possess in this world material wealth doesn't really have much meaning including false fame and even fame and success aren't that useful once you reach my age you'll see even though the young lady might be slightly frail your own health won't be as good either
就是说你拥有的世间的这些财富 俗世这些财富没有实际意义 包括虚名 功名也没有什么太大用 你真正到我这岁数以后 你看嘛 人家小妹妹虽然加微微 你自己身体不行了
right?
对不对
Positive people always move forward
积极人都向上
You move backward
你向下
That makes a difference
这就不一样了
Right?
对不对
So often, it's about the back-and-forth
所以很多的时候就是你争来争去
These things you argue over in your twenties and thirties
这些东西在你二三十岁争来争去啊
You go all out
费了八尽力啊
You spend your youth
耗费了青春
You sacrifice your moral standards
耗费了道德标准
At the cost of health
耗费了健康
to get these things
得到这些东西
in the end, you're just a pile of garbage
到头来你只不过是是一些垃圾而已
industrial waste
工业垃圾
e-waste
电子垃圾
cultural relics waste
文物垃圾
Look at what we use today, is any of it from the Ming and Qing dynasties?
你看咱们今天用的哪个是明清留下来的东西
Did the wealth of ancient people flow down to today?
那古代人那些财富流到今天了吗
Did the objects that ancient people were attached to survive to the present day?
古代人执着的那些物件留到今天了吗
Apart from what's buried with them,
除了带进坟墓的
is there anything else that can be dug up now?
现在能被人挖出来以外
What else has been left behind?
其他东西留下了吗
Wood and paper scraps,
木头纸片儿啊
copper and iron pieces, what really proved useful?
铜片铁片什么东西真正有用了
Right?
对不对
So, a lot of things were actually useless.
所以很多东西其实没有用啊
Wood rots,
木头会腐朽
and stone and ash won't be taken away.
石头灰到时候不会被扒走
The piece of cloth can catch fire.
衣服片会被烧着啊
A piece of paper would turn to ashes in no time. So let me tell you, being attached to material wealth, being obsessed with consumption, being fixated on the economic cycle, actually doesn’t hold much significance. So everyone should understand,
纸片更是也一把灰的事儿就没了 所以我跟你讲 执着于物质财富 执着于消费 执着于经济上的循环 其实本身没有多大意义 所以大家要明白
I’m not saying that we shouldn’t value fairness and justice.
我不是说大家不注重公平正义
I'm not saying
我也不是说啊
We shouldn't compete with the rich kids
咱们不要去跟富家子弟争
But I don't envy what they have
但是他们拥有的那些东西我不羡慕
I think what's most useful in life is
我认为人这一生就有什么最有用
What you have
你的东西
What truly contributes to the soul of human society
真正能对人类社会的灵魂构建起作用啊
That's what matters
这个有用
It influences people's thoughts
影响大家的思想
And helps everyone find a clear path forward
能够帮大家走出一条明路来
This is useful
这个有用
Leading the people to a well-off life
带领人民群众奔向小康的生活
This is really helpful
这个有用啊
Right?
是不是
So these things
所以这些东西啊
Actually, speaking of it
实际上来讲的话
A profound philosophical idea
一种高度的一种哲学思想
Material things don't represent happiness
就是物质并不能代表快乐
Materialism is a corrupt aspect of capitalism
物质是资本主义的一种腐朽的东西
What you have is pretty good
你拥有的很多是不错
it's about developing the economy
是发展经济
but you need to understand
但你要明白
material possession itself and spiritual cultivation
物质占有本身跟精神上的修为
can't be equated so to speak although we are now much more materially affluent if you compare it to before the liberation the abundance now is certainly much greater We have all these things now You can see that this camera costs me a little over 10,000 yuan
是不能划等号的啊 所以来讲的话 虽然物质上我们现在啊比较丰富了啊 那你跟解放前比 那现在解放绝对是极大丰富了 我们现在这些东西 你看我现在用这摄像机小1万块钱啊
Is it not true that my TV and gaming console cost over 10,000 yuan?
是不是我的电视游戏机1万多块钱
And the computer adds up to over 10,000 yuan as well
电脑加一块1万多块钱啊
If you think about it like in the past
你想以前似的
That would have made you a ten-thousand-yuan household months earlier
那要早几个月万元户啊
You know what I mean?
你说啊
But no matter what
但无论怎么样
Considering that era
那个时代来讲
There's no way you could have something this good
你不可能有这么好的东西
That was still a film camera
那还是胶片相机
Back then, TVs were so small
那时候那家里电视才多小
We had computers back then
那时候有电脑
What about phones?
有手机吗
No, we didn't
没有
So in terms of our actual daily lives
所以其实我们真正的生活上来讲
Things have become much more convenient
是便利程度便利多了
The internet 20 years ago couldn't even be used for ordering food
20年前的互联网也不能订餐
Shopping can also be quite a hassle
买东西也很费劲
and it even requires spending credit points or something like that
还得消耗什么信用点啊之类的
you have to exchange money for credit points first
还得先用钱换信用点
which is quite troublesome
很麻烦
and there’s no electronic online payment system
还没有电子的网上支付
so when it comes to many things today
所以很多东西来讲到今天来讲
in many aspects, actually
其实我们很多上面来讲的话
the gap between developed countries and the wealthy has been narrowed
跟发达国家跟有钱人之间是拉平了的
some services they used to have
以前他们拥有的一些服务啊
Just like this Didi ride-hailing service
就像这个滴滴网约车似的
It’s a service only Freemasons have
那是共济会会员才有的服务啊
They have their own special sedan cars
他们有会员的那种专门的轿子车
Outside the scope of regular taxis He also uses member services But now everyone has it The swallows that once nested in the halls of the noble Wang and Xie now fly into the homes of common people At least until today Do you really want to starve to death? In The New China Do you want to starve to death?
在这个出租车的范围之外 他也是用会员服务 但现在来讲人人都有了啊 旧时王谢堂前燕飞入平常百姓家 起码到今天 你说你真的想饿死 在新中国 你想饿死啊
That’s not an easy thing to do
那不是一件容易的事啊
It’s extremely difficult
非常不容易
If you say everyone is broke
你要说让大家没钱
It might be possible, but if you say everyone is hungry
有可能你要说这是大家我饿了
You can beg for food on the streets
在大街上讨点吃的
And they’ll feed you until you’re full
能给你喂撑了
That’s how it is
那东西就是这样
So when we talk about today
所以我们说到今天来讲的话
A lot of things don’t actually matter
好多东西它实际没有意义
So there’s no need to compete with them
所以没有必要跟他们去争
If they don’t want to compete, let them be
不争就不争了
They occupy those positions
他们占据那些位置
If they occupy them, so be it
占据了就占据了
They won’t stay there for long anyway
反正他们也待不了多久
Right?
对不对
Truly talented people
真正有才华的人
Truly capable people will still hold their ground in the hospital
真正有能力的人还是会坐镇医院当中的
So we need to find our own place
所以我们呢要找到我们自己的位置
Even though our current abilities are small
虽然我们现在的能力很渺小
We are just ordinary young people now
我们现在只是一个普通的年轻人
But remember, three pawns can force the king
但是记住三兵能逼宫啊
Accumulate the victories of small pawns
积累小兵的胜利
Small pawns working together
小兵之间相互协作啊
Can always make a big difference
其实总有大的作用
Don’t think you don’t have the major pieces
你别看你没有车马炮
You don’t have a Maserati
你没有玛莎拉蒂啊
Maybe you don’t have much
可能没有什么啊
Kurize might not have a BMW motorcycle
库里泽可能没有什么BMW的大摩托车
Maybe you don’t have a cannon
可能没有大炮啊
But I might just be a small cannon Maybe I don’t have a big cannon But we can still live a wonderful life Without letting down the people Without letting down the country There’s absolutely no problem So many things are just material wealth
你看我可能就是个小炮啊 可能没有大炮 但是咱们一样可以把这一生活的很精彩 无愧于人民 无愧于祖国 绝对没有问题啊 所以很多东西来讲不就是物质财富吗
Those high officials in the Ming and Qing dynasties
明清那些大官儿
How many were there in Beijing?
你在北京城多少啊
How many are left now?
你现在留下来有几个呀
Right?
对不对
Just those temples and such
也就那些庙啊什么的
The city walls were left
就留下了城墙
The gardens were left
留下了园子留下来了
But didn’t everything else disappear?
其他东西呢不也都没留下来吗
Didn’t they all sink to the bottom of the sea?
不也都早日沉入海底
Didn’t they all get buried in the yellow earth?
埋入黄土当中了吗
So don’t be attached to material wealth
所以不要执着于物质财富啊
Build up your spiritual cultivation
把精神上修为起来
Even though we might be nothing now
别看现在我们可能是什么都不是
One day we can soar to the sky
但是将来有一天我们能够一飞冲天啊
And make contributions to the people
能够为人民做出贡献